<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="WIC">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ca/act/wic/14005"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ca/act/wic/14005"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#california-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ca"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="14005"/>
          <FRBRname value="WIC"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ca/act/wic/14005/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ca/act/wic/14005/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ca/act/wic/14005/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ca/act/wic/14005/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="california-legislature" href="https://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov" showAs="California State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <division eId="div_9">
        <num>9</num>
        <part eId="part_3">
          <num>3</num>
          <chapter eId="chp_7">
            <num>7</num>
            <article eId="art_1">
              <num>1</num>
              <section eId="sec_14005">
                <num>14005</num>
                <heading>Section 14005</heading>
                <subsection eId="sec_14005__subsec_a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The health care benefits and services specified in this chapter, to the extent that such services are neither provided under any other federal or state law nor provided nor available under other contractual or legal entitlements of the person, shall be provided under this chapter to any person who is a resident of this state and is made eligible by the provisions of this article. It is the intent of the Legislature that a provider shall look to such other contractual or legal entitlements for payment before submitting a bill for payment
				under this chapter.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection eId="sec_14005__subsec_b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Any applicant for, or recipient of, Medi-Cal benefits who requests medical assistance for home and facility care shall meet the specific eligibility requirements for the receipt of medical assistance for home and facility care set forth in this chapter.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection eId="sec_14005__subsec_c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>This section shall be implemented pursuant to the requirements of Title XIX of the federal Social Security Act (42 U.S.C. Sec. 1396 et seq.), and any regulations adopted pursuant to that act, and only to the extent that federal financial participation is available.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection eId="sec_14005__subsec_d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>To the extent that regulations are necessary to implement this section, the department shall promulgate regulations using the nonemergency regulatory process described in Article 5 (commencing with Section 11346) of Chapter 3.5 of Part 1 of Division 3 of the Government
				Code.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection eId="sec_14005__subsec_e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>It is the intent of the Legislature that the provisions of this section shall apply prospectively to any individual to whom the act applies commencing from the date regulations adopted pursuant to this act are filed with the Secretary of State.
(Amended by Stats. 2008, Ch. 379, Sec. 2.   Effective January 1, 2009.)</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <authorialNote marker="history">
                  <p>(Amended by Stats. 2008, Ch. 379, Sec. 2.   Effective January 1, 2009.)</p>
                </authorialNote>
              </section>
            </article>
          </chapter>
        </part>
      </division>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>